Finding Aid for Dept. of Geological Sciences (University of Michigan) records 1913-1987
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Dept. of Geological Sciences (University of Michigan) records 1913-1987
University of Michigan. Dept. of Geological Sciences.
The Department of Geological Sciences provides both undergraduate and graduate students with field and lab experience. Begun in the 1830s, the separate geology and mineralogy programs merged in 1961. In 1979 the name was changed to Geological Sciences. Records of the department include faculty and staff meeting minutes, 1913-1987; correspondence, 1960-1972; and records pertaining to charges of research data fabrication against a former student.
90169 Bimu C26 2
6 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The record group was transferred to the library from the Department of Geology (Donor No. 1871 ) in March 1989. Additional material was transferred in June 2002.
The record group is open to research. One restricted folder of student records has been removed to vault storage.
The origin of the study of geology and mineralogy at the University of Michigan can be traced to the 1830s. Usually taught by one, sometimes two, academicians, these disciplines attracted to the university such influential scientists of the time as Mark W. Harrington, Israel Cook Russell, and Alexander Winchell.
The administrative formalizing of courses of study in geology and mineralogy did not take place until the early twentieth century and clearly followed the appointments of William Herbert Hobbs as professor of geology in 1906 and Edward H. Kraus as professor of mineralogy and petrography in 1910. Each of these individuals, through their skills as administrators and the forcefulness of their personalities were able to carve out separate administrative identities for their respective disciplines.
Geology and mineralogy continued as separate departments until 1961 when they merged to form the single Department of Geology and Mineralogy. In 1979, the department was renamed the Department of Geological Sciences. Today, the Department of Geological Sciences has a large and experienced staff, and offers course work in many fields of the geological sciences. Opportunities are available for both undergraduate and graduate research in the laboratory and in the field.
Department Chairmen: Geology
1906-1934 William H. Hobbs
1934-1939 Ermine C. Case
1940-1941 Irving D. Scott (acting)
1941-1951 Kenneth K. Landes
1951-1956 Edwin N. Goddard
1956-1961 James T. Wilson
Department Chairmen: Mineralogy
1910-1933 Edward H. Kraus
1933-1951 Walter F. Hunt
1951-1961 Lewis S. Ramsdell
Department Chairmen: Geological Sciences
1961-1966 Donald F. Eschman
1967-1971 John A. Dorr, Jr.
1971-1977 Charles I. Smith
1977-1978 Donald F. Eschman (acting)
1978-1981 William C. Kelly
1981-1988 Rob Van Der Voo
1988-1991 Henry Nathan Pollack
1992-1995 Rob Van Der Voo
1995-2000 David K. Rea
2000- Joel D. Blum
The Department of Geology record group covers the period from 1913 to 1987. A run of faculty and staff meeting minutes documents the entire period, while later series illuminate activities in the 1940s, 1960s, and 1970s. The records are arranged in the following series: Alumni Directory and Faculty Reprints, Departmental Correspondence, Faculty and Staff Meeting Minutes, and Wilson W. Crook, III Case Files.
Subjects:
Geology.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geological Sciences.; Geology--Study and teaching (Higher)--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
- Alumni Directory and Reprints 1947, 1944-1945
  The Alumni Directory and Reprints series (1944-1945, 1947, 0.2 linear feet) contains a 1947 directory of former students containing departmental news and information on alumni. Two bound volumes of reprints reflect the scholarly output of the faculty during the years 1944-1945.
  - Alumni Directory 1947 (Box 1)
  - Articles by Department of Geology Faculty 1944-1945, 2 volumes (Box 1)
- Departmental Correspondence 1960-1972
  The series Departmental Correspondence (1960-1972, 1.7 linear feet) consists of bound volumes of departmental correspondence, both incoming and outgoing. The correspondence is primarily from the administration of chairs Donald Eschman, John A. Dorr, and Charles I. Smith. The correspondence is largely administrative in content, though occasionally a scientific question is addressed.
  - 1962-1971 (A-G) (Box 1)
  - 1962-1971 (H-Z) (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - January-July 1967 (Box 1)
  - August-December 1967 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1968 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1968 (Box 2)
  - January-June 1969 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1969 (Box 2)
  - January-June 1970 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1970 (Box 2)
  - January-June 1971 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1971 (Box 2)
  - January-June 1972 (Box 2)
  - July-December 1972 (Box 2)
  - 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - 1986 (Box 2)
- Faculty Meeting Minutes 1913-1987
  The Faculty Meeting Minutes series (1913-1987, 1.5 linear feet) provides the most comprehensive documentation of Department of Geology activities and issues beginning in 1913. Minutes from 1913 to 1936 are handwritten while later minutes are typed. Prior to 1961 the minutes are exclusively of the Department of Geology. After 1961, the minutes are of the combined departments of geology and mineralogy. The minutes also include various related documents, policy papers, proposals, evaluations, and reports relating to curriculum, instruction, staffing, research, and facilities.
  - 1913-1935 (Box 2)
    (3 binders)
  - 1935-1981 (Box 3)
  - 1981-1987, 16 volumes; 3 volumes; 3 folders (Box 4)
- Wilson W. Crook, III Case Files 1974-1984
  The Wilson W. Crook, III Case Files series (1974-1984, 2.8 linear feet) relates to charges of research fabrication leveled against one of the department's students, Wilson W. Crook, III, the rescinding of his degree, and litigation relating to that action. Records include background on the case and legal records from the subsequent litigation involving Crook and the University of Michigan. Included are articles, case records, correspondence relating to the case, a bound description of the charges, Crook's dissertation, court exhibits, Crook's experiment data and research notes, and a talk given in Tucson by Crook in 1977.
  - Documents in Support of Charges of Fabrication of Data against Wilson W. Crook, III
    - Documents 1-26 (Box 4)
    - Documents 27-38 (Box 4)
  - Chronological File
    - July 1977-March 1980, 3 volumes (Box 4)
    - April 1980-November 1980 (Box 5)
  - Articles
    - Case Related 1980-1984 (Box 5)
    - Similar Cases 1980-1984 (Box 5)
  - Case Records
    - Crook vs. Peacor, et al 1983, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Crook vs. Peacor, et al 1983, 1 volumes; 1 folders (Box 5)
    - Crook vs. University of Michigan 1980-1984, 4 volumes; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Uyidi vs. University of Toronto 1980-1981 (Box 5)
    - Waliga, et al vs. Board of Trustees of Kent State University 1984 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 5)
    - E. Wm. Heinrich 1974-1979 (Box 5)
    - Akira Kato (Box 5)
    - Law Offices
      - Bushnell, Gage, Doctoroff, Reizerd & Byington 1980-1982 (Box 5)
      - Davis & Fajen, P. C. 1980-1984 (Box 5)
      - John R. Dethmers 1980-1982 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous 1983 (Box 5)
    - Southern Methodist University 1974 (Box 5)
    - Texas Bureau of Economic Geology 1979 (Box 5)
    - United States Department of the Interior 1981 (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan 1979-1984 (Box 5)
  - Crook Miscellaneous Files 1975-1977 (Box 6)
  - Description of Charges (Box 6)
  - Dissertation "The Geology, Mineralogy, and Geochemistry of the Rare-Earth Pegmatites, Llano and Burnet Counties, Texas," 1977 (Box 6)
  - Exhibits (index) (Box 6)
  - Experiment Data
    - Computer Output 1979 (Box 6)
    - Mineral Data
      - Chlorine and Fluorine-Rich Jarosite 1976-1977 (Box 6)
      - Cobalt Chloride Hydrate Albrittonite 1977 (Box 6)
      - Rowlandite 1976-1978 (report, correspondence) (Box 6)
      - Tengerite 1976 (Box 6)
      - Texasite 1976 (report, correspondence) (Box 6)
      - Thalenite-Bokanite-Iimoriite 1978-1979 (Box 6)
        (report, correspondence)
      - Yttrocrasite 1976-1977 (Box 6)
    - X-Ray Data-Thesis Minerals (Box 6)
    - Xeroxes of Probe and X-Ray Data 1976-1979 (Box 6)
      (abstract, calculations, computer program)
  - Research Notes (Box 6)
  - Student Records 1974-1980
    [SR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2055 ]
  - Tucson Talk 1977 (Box 6)